Getting muscular, also sometimes
referred to as natural bodybuilding, or
getting a jacked physique, [music] or
getting ripped, or getting shredded, or
getting aesthetic, or getting swole, or
getting buff, or getting yolked, or
getting peeled, or making gains, or
whatever people will call it 2 months
from now is actually pretty easy. You
can see that over time, getting jacked
has become less of an achievement and
more of an expectation because pretty
much everyone works out now. My guess is
because house prices are unaffordable.
Friends are basically impossible to make
outside of school. Your hobbies aren't
interesting unless they make money.
Everyone who doesn't look like a model
is [music] chopped. Marriage rates are
plummeting. And it's hard to make a
living when everyone's fighting for only
a small chance at getting not a piece of
the pie, but a piece of a piece of a
piece of a piece of the pie. But at
least we can all get big muscles, look
in the mirror, and tell ourselves that
at least we're doing something right in
this world.
Uh, a common question most people wonder
when they begin is how long does it take
to get muscular? And that really depends
on how optimal your workouts are. Your
age, your gender, your genetics, your
diet, your sleep, your height, your
starting body weight, and most
importantly, it depends on what you
define as muscular. If you have average
expectations, as in you just want to see
a noticeable change in your physique,
then it probably takes about 6 months.
If you want to really visually look like
you work out, then probably at least one
year. If you want to look like the
muscular people you see from time to
time in real life, two to three years.
If you want to look like the shredded
people you see every day on the
internet, probably 4 to 600 milligrams
per week. And if you want to be truly
happy with how your physique looks, you
are probably asking for too much. No
matter what your goal is, one of the
saving graces about building muscle is
that progress is fast at the beginning
and exponentially slows down the more
muscular you get. That means someone
who's been training for 2 years is much
much bigger and stronger than they were
at the beginning. This beginning portion
is called newbie gains where you can do
pretty much any recommended workout
routine and as long as you make a
conscious effort to lift hard, sleep,
and eat protein, you can't not build
muscle. Usually during the next 2 years
of training, you do grow a lot and you
do have noticeable changes, but it's not
as fast as the progress you made during
your first 2 years. If this part was
[music] newbie gains, this part is maybe
gains. Here, you can no longer afford to
have a bad diet and a pump and dump
workout schedule where you skip weeks at
a time and just do whatever machine is
open. You actually have to start
measuring your progress. Tracking your
sets and reps, [music] sticking to a
good diet, not skipping days, not
skipping sleep, not watching videos
about working out as a replacement for
working out.
And lastly, in most cases, someone who's
trained for 8 years looks barely any
different from how they looked after
year four or five. This is the stage at
which you're basically just maintaining
and looking for ways to optimize and eek
out a little more progress. Either that
or you get fed up of how slow you're
building muscle. So just to feel some
sense of progress again, you switch to
something entirely different like
powerlifting or you start rock climbing
or you hit the courts or you hop on a
cycle or you hop on a cycle or one day
after working out you come home, relax
and hop on the most comprehensive
vehicle combat game ever made, War
Thunder. If you're looking to dive deep
into the depths of military history,
look no further. I don't know how they
have the budget to make it free since it
literally has thousands of military
tanks, planes, helicopters, ships, and
each one is intricately modeled to
attack and take damage like it would in
real life with realistic damage systems
where each hit matters. Something you
can see for yourself using War Thunder's
X-ray feature. Now you can see in style
how you got absolutely destroyed or
landed the perfect hit. They literally
developed their own in-house engine just
so that these graphics can still run
with no lag on whatever machine you have
right now. What I really like about it
is if you just want some simple PvP
gameplay, they have an arcade mode. If
you want a little bit more of a
challenge, they have a realistic mode.
And if you're really into military
history and vehicles, they have a
simulator mode. So, it's kind of like
three games in one. Join a community of
over 70 million players today for free
on your PC, PlayStation, Xbox, or even
mobile devices. Just sign up using the
links in the description or the pinned
comment. And on PC and console, you get
a massive bonus pack. It's for anyone
who's new to the game or hasn't played
in 6 months. It'll grant you the
exclusive vehicle decorator Eagle of
Valor, 100,000 Silver Lions, 7 days of
premium account, and more. And that's a
limited time offer, so don't miss that.
Link down below. So, where was I? Oh,
yeah. Hopping on a cycle. No one should
actually do it. It's basically swapping
your vital life sustaining organs for a
little bit extra muscle and strength,
which no one will actually care about
anyway cuz you didn't get it naturally.
Even if your excuse is that you want to
become something like a professional
bodyguard, where you really need a lot
of muscle, like way [music] more than
the average person, imagine how
embarrassing it would be to juice up and
shave years off of your life and still
not even get the job cuz you're too
small. It would literally be impossible
to come back from that kind of thing.
So, you're better off not even
considering going down that road.
Anyway, the reason why I say building
muscle pretty much all comes down to
consistency is that being consistent,
even just two times a week, even with
some unoptimized 90minute full body
routine that you find on the first page
of Google, will eventually get you to
fill out most of your muscular
potential. Because first of all,
everyone on Earth who has ever lifted
consistently [music] at least two times
a week for an extended period of time at
some point began to take pride in it.
And after a few years, it usually ends
up making about 25% to 90% of your
personality. You'll very quickly realize
what progressive overload is. You need
to increase the weight you're lifting or
the reps you're doing to keep making
gains. You'll start looking up diet
tips. You'll start learning about
different exercise variations. You'll
start researching what the optimal
protein sources are, what the optimal
protein per pound of body weight is, and
you'll probably even accidentally get
sucked into a niche fitness rabbit hole.
So, no, you really don't have to know
anything about bulking or cutting or
optimal exercise form or optimal workout
splits when you start going to the gym.
Because as long as you go consistently
and never stop, you will voluntarily
start seeking out that information. Even
the people who study all that stuff
before working out for the first time
will still end up researching everything
again just cuz it's one of the few times
you can watch videos about one of your
hobbies while also feeling like you're
doing something productive. Another
reason why working out consistently is
more important than working out
optimally is that we're all going to the
same place anyway. Since I said before,
if you train well and have a decent
diet, your visible progress starts
maxing out after about 6 to 8 years of
training. And honestly, it's probably
faster than that, but I'm trying to be
nice. So, eventually, we're all going to
get pretty close to our max potential.
And whether you do 20 sets per muscle
group per week or you just do 10 or you
do 40, the only thing that changes is
how long it'll take you to get to that
max potential. In fact, pretty much
everything when it comes to muscle
building is diminishing returns. Which
means as you do more and more sets for
an exercise, each additional set has
less and less of an effect. As you eat
more and more grams of protein, each
additional gram is less and less useful.
As you add more and more workout days to
your schedule, each additional day
builds less and less muscle. As you
watch more and more YouTube videos about
the gym, each additional
Anyway, if you look at this chart, uh it
says four sets per muscle group per week
is the minimum effective dose needed to
increase your muscle size. And that's
fractional sets, meaning for your
biceps, a set of bicep curls counts as
one set. But a set of pull-ups, which is
meant for your back muscles, will also
count towards half a set of biceps.
Since your biceps are one of the muscles
that are active during pull-ups, you can
tell cuz on the machine it'll show a
transparent guy with those biceps
highlighted in red. So, as you can see,
the more and more sets you do, the less
and less efficient it gets. If going all
the way down here is almost double the
effort with barely any additional muscle
size gained, then you might as well
stick around here for your biceps to
save time and energy for other muscle
groups. After all, the ceiling for how
much muscle you can gain in your
lifetime is still basically the same, no
matter how long it takes you. So, what's
really the point of rushing to get
there? I mean, obviously, you can get
your dream physique faster, but even
then, you'll still have to keep working
out to maintain that physique. If you
ask a gym bro, "Do you ever plan to stop
working out?" They'd be like, "No, bro.
Even if you're not getting bigger, bro,
the health benefits, bro, like the bone
density, the glucose regulation, they
last your whole life, bro. Also, bro,
not roll lifting, bro, kills your gains,
bro. Well said. So, if you never plan to
stop working out, all you have to do to
max out your potential is to make
consistent progress, even if it's slow
progress. The only thing you have to
avoid is moving backwards, which is
caused by long periods where you miss
workouts, you stop training certain
muscle groups.
Uh, you don't eat properly, and you
don't get enough sleep. Cuz the main
reason a lot of people get stuck looking
the same for multiple years in a row is
they start working out six days a week,
then they stop working out for a month,
then recover the lost progress, and stop
working out again. And they keep
repeating this forever, doing the same
weight for the same reps every session.
Compare that with someone who works just
two times a week, but never misses a
week, and always tries to do an extra
rep or a little extra weight. Since
their progress is always consistently
going up and never down, they will
slowly but surely max out their
potential. So, the next time you feel
like quitting the gym cuz there's too
many sweats, squatting 400 lb, and
making the t sound every time they go up
like a pressure washer, just know that
you're only about 3 to 5 years away from
being a sweat yourself. So, now I'm just
going to answer the most common
questions I found on Google for how to
gain muscle. And if you're doubting my
credibility here, I've gotten one pixel
wider since the last video. What's the
best workout split? It depends on how
many days a week you work out. My
favorite split is whatever machines are
open, but these are some good ones. Does
calisthenics work? Yeah, but it's harder
to make measurable progress cuz you're
not able to add weight as easily. When
does the soreness go away after a few
weeks? How do you gain weight? A lot of
people oversimplify the answer to this
question by just saying lift hard, sleep
more, eat more. But I think the answer
is a lot more complicated and varies
from person to person. My suggestions
will be lifting hard, sleeping more, and
eating more. Is cardio necessary?
Thanks again to War Thunder for being
today's sponsor. Remember to use my
links down below to download the game
free for PC, console, and mobile. Plus,
if you're on PC or console and you're a
new player or you haven't played for 6
months, you get to claim a bonus pack.
I'm also collecting donations in the
form of subscribes to fund the next
video.